《上海正午》
(1881年 中国 紫禁城)
公主驾到!
爹  您把我许配给这样的人?
不可能的  我不会嫁给他的
既然皇上那么看重他  就让皇上嫁给他好了
公主点头  青蛙说:
The princess nodded, and the frog said
"你一旦答应  就必须要做到"
"That which you have promised, you must perform."
非常好  继续读
Very good. Keep reading.
公主俯身亲吻了青蛙
"So the princess leaned in and kissed the frog,
这时  青蛙变成一位英俊的王子
"but as she did, he became a handsome prince
后来他们骑马到了他的王国
"and they rode off to his kingdom,
从此以后一起幸福地生活
where they lived happily ever after. "
从此以后一起幸福地生活...
Happily ever after.
没有像"从此以后一起幸福地生活"这样的事
There's no such thing as " happily ever after."
不会发生在一位真正的公主身上
Not for a real princess.
我这个公主的父亲想要我嫁的人永远是一只青蛙
The prince my father wants me to marry will always be a frog.
我的提议仍然有效  我会帮你去美国
My offer still stands. I will help you get to America.
- 美国?  - 那太好了
- America?  - That's very kind.
但是我们就要没时间了
But we're running out of time.
我知道有一艘要驶往美国的船  但是我们必须今晚就走
I know of a ship bound for America, but we must leave tonight.
- 今晚就走?  - 我们得抓紧  公主
- Leave tonight?  - We must hurry, Princess.
快点  公主
Hurry, Princess.
公主!
你叫我停?
奴才不敢!
两个月以后的今天  中午十二点
你们一定要把十万根金条啊...
送到内华达州卡森市的教会里
否则的话  公主性命难保!
万岁!
奉天承运  皇帝诏曰
特派三位最勇敢的皇家卫兵
陪同皇家翻译  一同前往亚美利加国保护佩佩公主
- 蒙古汉  - 喳
- Mung Goo Hi. - Yes.
- 赵超  - 喳
- Zhou Hei. - Yes.
- 周陆  - 喳
- Chow Lu. - Yes.
出列
散
接旨
谢主隆恩  万岁万岁万万岁
姜文  你来干什么?
没有留住公主是我的责任  请允许我一同前往搭救公主
这...不可能
队长
我老了  只有姜文这么一个侄子
您就开开恩让他陪我去一趟吧  啊?
他还能帮着搬搬行李哪
也好
让那些洋人们教育教育他
是是是
陪我到军机处报到!
喳
(美国  内华达州)
(七周之后)
是的  没错  就是它
Oh, yeah. Oh, yeah, that's it.
好  很好
Okay. Great. Great. Okay.
来这里  看看这个  在这上面花费了很多时间的
Come here. Look at this. Spent a lot of time on this.
现在  专心点  因为我不想出任何的差错
Now, pay attention, 'cause I don't want any mistakes.
我已经计算好了火车的速度  和我们的马的速度
Now, I've calculated the speed of the train and the speed of our horses.
我们会在这个向量处会合  唯一的变量是风
We meet at this vector. The only variable is the wind.
- 技术上讲  如果骑马到这里...  - 这是火车?
- Technically, if you travel over here on the horses...  - Is this the train?
那我们就开始即兴表演吧  就像我们以前经常做的那样
All right. We're just gonna wing it... like we always do.
赶上火车  然后再跳上去
Ride down, jump on the train,
把钱抢到手了  回去逛窑子  可以了吧?
hoorah the money, head back to the cathouse, all right?
- 嗯嗯 - 走吧  快点  开始行动
- Mm-hmm.  - Let's go. Come on. Move out. Go!
你还好吗?  有点紧张?  新手有点紧张没关系
You okay? Nervous? It's all right to be nervous when you're new.
你不会有事的  我会照看着你的
You'll be okay. I'll keep an eye on you.
你要做的就是听我指挥  好了  快点  抢匪们
All you gotta do is follow my lead. All right, look alive, outlaws!
公主俯身亲吻了青蛙
"So the princess leaned in and kissed the frog,
这时  青蛙变成一位英俊的王子
"but as she did, he became a handsome prince,
后来他们骑马到了他的王国
"and they rode off to his kingdom,
从此以后一起幸福地生活
where they lived happily ever after. "
举起手来  女士们先生们
Reach for the sky, ladies and gentlemen!
- 谁要是...  - 谁要是碰下枪  我就轰掉他的脑袋
Touch that gun and I'll blow your god damn head off!
华莱士你干什么?  我可是你们之中唯一可以这样说话的人
What are you doin'? I sorta like to be the only guy that talks, Wallace.
- 好吧  对不起  - 这就好  没事
- All right. I'm sorry.  - That's okay. That's okay. Good.
别担心  走吧  快点  大个  我们走
Don't worry. Come on, come on. Big 'Un, let's go.
为什么这个新手在喊话?  你在哪儿找到这个家伙的?
Why is the new guy talking? Where did you get this guy?
你知道我是唯一能喊话的人  好了  大家都保持镇静
You know I'm the only one who talks. Okay, everybody keep calm.
你在想要向我开火  对吧?
You think you're gonna shoot me? Is that right?
你在这里弄到什么了?  是吗  你弄到了这把枪?
What you got right in here? Yeah, you got this gun?
你想用这把枪干点什么是吧?
You think you're gonna do something with that gun?
快点  淑女  你在纱线里藏了什么吧?
Come on, Lady Bird. You got anything in here besides yarn?
- 都拿出来  都拿出来  都给我拿出来 - 嘿
- You got it out for me!  - Hey!
过来  过来  我们不拿女人的东西
Come here. Come here. We don't steal from women.
走开  靠边站
Get over here. Take that side.
伸出你的手  伸出你的手
Give me your hand. Give me your hand.
刚才的事真对不起  我道歉
I'm so sorry about that. I apologize.
你第一次看到抢匪?
First time you've seen an outlaw?
害怕?  而且还有点兴奋?
Scared? Kind of excited too?
或者都有?  是的
All mixed up? Yeah.
我们上次抢劫火车的时候都是裸体的  当时外面很热
Last train we robbed, we were naked, it was so hot out.
有某个东西...
Yeah, it was somethin'.
是的  开始时就是这样的
Yeah, it's got my initials right there.
你在看什么?
What are you lookin' at?
等等  住手  你在哪儿找到这个家伙的?
Wait! Stop! Where did you get this guy?
- 德克萨斯  - 德克萨斯?  你是精神病吗?
- Texas.  - Texas? Are you insane?
开枪打我吧  我都不知道  我们在这里在干什么
Just shoot me now, 'cause I don't understand what we're doing here.
先生先生先生先生  过来过来过来  坐下
Sir, sir, sir, sir. Come here, come here, come here. Sit down.
- 对不起  我喝水呀  - 先生  坐下
- Excuse me.  - Sir, sit down.
- 怎么了?  华莱士  你在干什么?  - 我只是在即兴表演
- What happened? Wallace, what are you doing?  - I'm just wingin' it.
不  我们不是那样即兴表演的
No! That's not how we wing it!
不要再即兴表演了  住手  过来  大个子
No more winging it! Stop! Come on, Big 'Un.
- 你已经没有即兴表演的权利了  - 该死的
- You've lost your "winging it" privileges.  - Damn.
该死的
Damn!
我叔叔呢?
叔叔  叔叔  叔叔你没事吧  叔叔!
你们谁做的?
谁杀了我的叔叔?  谁干的?
Who killed my uncle? Who did this?
把炸药给我  把炸药给我
Give me the dynamite. Give me the dynamite.
不不不  你留在这里  你不用跟过来
No, no, no, no. You stay here. You don't get to come.
- 看着华莱士  - 看着这里
- Keep an eye on Wing Nut.  - Hey, Blue, looky here!
很好
Okay.
- 谁杀了我的叔叔?  - 这是什么  东方快车吗?
- Who killed my uncle?  - What the hell is this, the Orient Express?
- 抓住他  - 过来
- Get him!  - Come here!
保险箱就快爆炸了
Wh...Hey! The safe's getting ready to blow!
准备好去拿我们的劳动成果吧
Get ready to reap the fruits of our labor.
抓住他  我们上
Move it! Let's go!
罗伊  你把我们的成果炸飞了
Roy, you just blew the shit out of our fruits.
该死
Oh, shit.
我们得抓到那个中国佬
We got a Chinaman to catch.
站住  站住
Stop! Stop!
站住  别动  转过来
Stop! Stop! Turn around!
转过来
Turn around!
到底怎么...
What the...
- 你是谁?  - 罗伊
- Who are you?  - Hey, Roy!
你不担心吗?  我帮你掩护
Don't you worry about a thing! I got you covered!
不
No!
滚下去吧  宝贝  滚下去
Roll, baby, roll!
别动  奥班诺  现在是我说了算
Reach for the sky, O'Bannon! It's my gang now!
我不明白
I don't understand.
你说你的朋友有很多财产的
You said your friend had a large estate.
他是有啊
He does.
- 他到底是干什么的?  - 好吧  你可以说他是一个...
- What exactly does he do?  - Well, you could say...
慈善家
he's a philanthropist.
他帮助中国的移民  靠自己的能力生活
He helps Chinese immigrants get back on their feet.
欢迎来到美国  公主
Welcome to America, Princess.
罗方?
Lo Fong.
原谅我没有行屈膝礼
Forgive me if I do not bow.
卡尔文  这个男人是卖...
Calvin, this man is a trai...
卖国贼
Traitor.
为什么?  因为他从紫禁城逃了出来?
Why? Because he ran away from the Forbidden City?
你的酬金放在桌子上了  安德鲁斯先生
Your reward is on the table, Mr. Andrews.
现在你必须加倍付酬金  否则我就杀了她
Well, now you're gonna have to double it, or I'm gonna kill her.
安德鲁斯先生  我们中国人...
One thing about the Chinese, Mr. Andrews  ...
我们不会谈判两次的
We do not renegotiate.
如果你觉得我会答应你什么
Whatever you think I'm going to do for you,
那你就错了
you're wrong.
简直是场噩梦
It was just like a nightmare.
你不会相信我所说的
You wouldn't believe it if I told you.
我的同伙把我扔在沙漠里  我感觉所有的牛仔都恨我入骨
My gang left me in the desert. I felt like all the other cowboys hated my guts.
每个人都是...我只是很想你们  很想你们几个
Everyone was...I just missed you. I missed all of you.
我们也很想你  罗伊
We missed you too, Roy.
疗养时间到了
I think it's medication time.
过来  魔女
Come here, devil woman.
你好调皮
Oh! Ooh, that's naughty.
小心  小心点
Ohh. Ow, careful. Careful with that.
小心...
Ow, ow. Careful. Ow.
该死  秃鹫在啃我的脑袋
Holy crap! The vultures are eating my head!
救命  救命  我的同伴抛弃了我
Help! Help! My gang buried me!
他们把我留下来等死
They left me for dead!
谢天谢地  我还以为你是幻觉
Oh, thank heavens. I thought you were a mirage.
- 快  水  - 是你
- Oh, come on. Water.  - You.
- 你杀了我的叔叔  - 不
- You killed my uncle!  - Bull!
那都是华莱士干的
That was Wallace all the way.
- 他是你们这帮强盗中的一个  - 他并不是我们的同伙
- He was one of your bandits.  - He wasn't part of my gang.
他是一个新手  他像马路上的蜥蜴那么疯狂
He was a new guy. He's crazy as a road lizard.
- 你活该等死  - 等等
- You deserve to die.  - Hold on a second.
你知道一件谁都没提起的事吗?
You know what no one's saying here?
在火车上我有个机会能杀了你的  但是我却没有杀你
I had a chance to kill you on that train, and I chose not to.
因为我不是个野蛮人
'Cause I'm not a barbarian.
- 你要去哪儿?  - 卡森市
- Hey! Where are you going?  - Carson City.
我挖洞到中国都比你到卡森市还近
I'm closer to diggin' myself to China than you are to gettin' to Carson City.
- 嘿  - 怎么走?
- Hey!  - Which way?
这还差不多  把我挖出来我就指给你
Hey, that's better. Dig me out and I'll show you.
怎么走?
Which way?
你看见那...那座山了吗?
You see the... mountains over there?
卡森市就在山的那边
Carson City is on the other side.
好了  把我挖出来  我们的交易就结束了
All right, dig me out. I kept my end of the bargain.
把我挖出来
Dig me out.
自己挖吧
Dig.
- 拜托  - 别说话  慢慢挖吧
- Come on!  - Don't talk. Just dig.
快走  快走啊
快点走  快点走!
我没告诉过你不能在克劳族的地盘上玩吗?
对不起  父亲
他打败了六个克劳族人
空手打败的!
他为什么穿着裙子?
卡森市...在...哪里?
Where is Carson City?
他刚才说的很慢  好像是在寻求帮助
但是我还是不懂他到底在说些什么
把和睦烟斗给他  也许能让他闭嘴
(和睦烟斗: 印第安人用来表示和睦)
这烟劲可真冲
大家早
女儿
你的丈夫是个"穿着裙子战斗的男人"
不用每天都陪着他
你的职责是看好他
是  父亲
不行啊  我跟...
他昨天晚上却没有喊过冤
小女儿  把结婚礼物带来
别烦恼了  他可能不是很合适  不过至少不是白人
我想你可能饿了
I thought you might be hungry.
点心
我不饿
You were wrong.
如果我们能达成某种协议
You would find me a much better host
你会发现我是个更好客的主人
if we could come to some sort of an arrangement.
协议?
An arrangement?
就像你和铁路上工作的那些奴隶达成的那种?
Like the one you have with the slaves working on this railroad?
到时这些人就可以自由离开了
These people are free to leave.
你想从我这里得到什么?
What do you want with me?
一旦得到皇帝的黄金  我的工作就结束了
Once I have the emperor's gold, my work will be complete.
公主
Princess.
现在应该让你去和你的臣民们在一起了
I think it is time for you to be among your people.
他们看起来不像我看到过的印第安人  杰迪戴亚
They don't look like any injuns I ever seen, Jedediah.
那是因为他们不是印第安人  他们是犹太人
That's because they're not injuns, woman! They're Jews!
你  留下
You, stay.
伙计们  看看他
You guys, get a load of this.
这儿是卡森市吗?
Is this Carson City?
不  这儿不是卡森市  酋长
No, this ain't Carson City, Chief.
你得去别的地方打你的烈酒了
You're gonna have to get your firewater somewhere else.
好了  罗伊  下注吧
All right, Roy, ante up.
在外面待着吧
And stay out!
你这么快就回来了  爬虫
You bounce back fast, kimosabe.
你在这里做什么?  我还以为你去了卡森市呢
What are you doin' here? I thought you were going to Carson City.
你...你给我指了条坏路
You! You gave me bad directions!
不对  应该说我给你指了条"错"路
No, I gave you wrong directions.
你想要回你的牙签吗?
You want your toothpicks back?
- 你太神经了  来这儿把...  - 把它还给我
- You got a lot of nerve, comin' in here with that...  - Give it back to me!
这是什么?
Ain't that somethin'?
把你的手拿开
Take your hand off me.
我只是想去卡森市
Hey, I just want to go to Carson City!
送你一程
You're goin' for a ride!
不
No!
好  很好
Yes! Yeah!
好  太好了
Yes! Yes!
不  不
No! No!
对不起  对不起
Sorry! I'm sorry!
你...
You!
- 谁先捣的乱?  - 中国佬
- Who in the hell started this?  - The Chinaman.
把书还给我  放我出去!
把书还给我  放我出去
Let me out! Give me the book back!
我必须去卡森市救公主
I have to go to Carson City to rescue the princess!
你们抓错人了  我不该被关在这儿
You've got the wrong person! I don't belong here!
让我出去啊!
继续说汉语吧  这很有效  他们就要放你出去了
Keep goin' with the Chinese. That's workin'. They're about to let you out.
- 把书还给我  - 他喊得这么大声  就把书还给他吧
- Give me the book back!  - For cryin' out loud, just give him the book back, please
- 这样就能让我们安静一会儿  - 把门打开
- If it'll give us some peace and quiet...Forget about it.  - Open it up!
他们不会还你书了  放弃吧
They're not givin' you the book back. Drop the book.
你已经浪费我够多时间了
I wasted enough time with you
什么?  我浪费了你很多时间?  关我什么事啊?
What? You've wasted enough time with me? What about me?
把书还给我
Give me the book!
- 听我说  别喊了  - 把书还给我
- Listen for a second. Stop!  - Give me the book! Hey!
听着  别喊了  你不是在东方  明白吗
Listen! Stop! You're not in the East, okay?
你不是在中国  这是西方
You're not in China. This is the West.
太阳虽然不是在这里升起来  但它在这里落下
The sun doesn't rise here, it sets here
你就快让他们吊死我们了  然后你就能要回那本书了是吧?
and you're closer to getting us hung than you are getting that book back, okay?
现在只是...我喜欢...
Now, just...I like that.
这正是我想说的  你太紧张了
That's what I'm talking about. You're wound so tight.
你是我见过的最暴躁的家伙  放松一下嘛
You're the most irritable guy I've ever been around. Just relax for a second.
这样十分钟后你就能出去继续歇斯底里了  我保证
Take ten minutes, and then you can go back to screaming, I promise.
到时我会陪你一起疯的  好了  放松一下
I'll join you. Okay, just relax for a second.
来吧  坐下来
Come on, sit down.
来吧
Come on.
放松一下
Just relax.
你是在放松吗?
Is that relaxed?
你神情很僵硬
You look sort of rigid there.
你知道吗?  我们都没给对方留下好印象
You know what? We got off on the wrong foot.
让我们试着重新认识吧
Let's try to start again.
伙计  你很能打
Man, you sure can fight.
我从来没看到过像你这样的
I've never seen anything like that.
就像...
It was...
我想称赞你一下
I'm trying to give you a compliment.
你还没有因为我给你指错路而发疯吗?
You're not still mad about me pointin' you in the wrong direction, are you?
拜托  你听到这种笑料应该笑的
Come on. You gotta be able to laugh at stuff like that.
就像我在沙漠中  我毫无怨恨  我只觉得好笑
Like me in the desert. I don't hold any grudges. I laugh about it.
我并不生你的气  你只留下筷子让我等死
I'm not angry at you. You just left me there with chopsticks to die.
独自寂寞  当时只有我和在啃我脑袋的兀鹫
Roy, all by his lonesome. Just me and the buzzards pickin 'at my head.
你是个很沉默的人  对吧?
You're a very silent man, aren't you?
你并不想在那个酒吧中看见我是吧?
You weren't expecting to see old Roy in that bar, were you?
诚实点  是吗?
Be honest. Were you? Huh?
你真的用筷子逃脱的吗?
Did you really use those chopsticks?
你最好能相信
You better believe it.
你笑了  这个玩笑很有趣  我要记住它
Now you laugh. That's funny. I gotta remember that one.
好了  你到底是谁?
So, who are you?
我是中国皇帝的皇家卫兵
I'm Imperial Guard to the Emperor of China.
中国
China.
那是什么书?
What's with the book?
那书是佩佩公主的
The book belongs to Princess Pei Pei
- 谁?  - 佩佩公主
- Who?  - Princess Pei Pei.
她在紫禁城里被绑架出来
She was kidnapped from the Forbidden City.
紫禁城?  我喜欢紫禁城
Forbidden City? I like that, the Forbidden City.
公主被绑架了  好神秘  继续说
A princess kidnapped. It's so mysterious. Oh, go ahead.
皇帝派我们接回她
The emperor sent us to get her back.
我们?  你指你火车上的朋友?
Us? You mean your friends from the train?
他们也是皇家卫兵
They are also Imperial Guards.
他们要在四天内将黄金带到卡森市
They have four days to bring the gold to Carson City
- 什么黄金?  - 赎回公主的黄金
- What gold?  - The gold for the princess.
那些黄金...黄金是在火车上吗?
The gold...Was the gold on the train?
是的
Yes.
有多少黄金?
How much gold?
十万根
One hundred thousand pieces.
先生  先生  可以把那本书给我们吗?
Sir? Sir? Could you hand us that book, please?
先生  这是个误会  他...
Sir, there's been a mistake. He has...
先生...对...
Sir...Yeah.
我们要拿回那本书  然后再要把你从这里弄出去
We're gonna get that book, and we're gonna get you out of here.
- 你帮助我逃脱?  - 是的
- You help me escape?  - Shh. Yes.
- 为什么?  - 为什么?  我会告诉你为什么
- Why?  - Why? I'm gonna tell you why.
因为在这个世界上有一些事是错误的
Because there are some things in this world that are just wrong,
而绑架公主就是其中之一
and stealing a princess is one of them.
是的  那是错误的
Yeah. That's wrong.
我再告诉你件事  我很抱歉给你指错路  让你翻过那座山
I'll tell you another thing. I feel guilty about leading you up that mountain.
我在胡想什么啊  在那里我们浪费了多少时间啊?
What was I thinking? How much time did we waste there?
这太蠢了  也不好笑  对吧?
That was stupid. It wasn't funny. All right?
现在坐好了让我想想怎么逃出去
Now, sit tight and let me figure this out.
好了  快点  罗伊
All right, come on, Roy.
也许  也许我假装不舒服  然后在守卫进来时攻击他们
Maybe...Maybe I pretend to be sick, then attack the guards when they come in.
你是指囚犯装病的那种老套?
Okay, you mean the sick prisoner routine?
是吗  这个在中国还有效吗?
Yeah. Does that still work in China?
在这里用可能会死人的
'Cause here it's sorta been done to death.
- 我又有了个主意  - 不不...
- I have another idea.  - No, no, no, no, no.
我告诉你怎么帮我
Here's how you help me.
你待在那边  让我自己在这边想想
You stay on your side of the room, let me figure it out over here.
好了  你去那边慢慢玩吧
Okay, you play over there.
思考  思考  这里有什么可以用上的  对了
Think. Think. What do we got here? Oh, yeah.
很好
Okay.
有木头  有一面木头做成的墙
We got wood. We got a wall made out of wood.
很好  还有枕头
That's good. Oh, we got pillows.
有枕头  床单  还有床单和床垫
We got pillows, sheets. We got the sheets and the mattress.
好了  把他们放在一起  好好想想  这些都算上...
Okay, let's put it all together. Let's think. Add it up, add it up.
得出了什么  得出了什么
What do we got? What do we got?
你在做什么?  住手  住手
What are you doing? Stop! Stop!
- 你到底在做什么?  - 嘘
- What are you doing?  - Shh.
- 帮我拿着这个  - 不不  这是你的衬衫  自己拿着吧
- Hold this for me.  - No, no. That's your shirt. You hold it.
我喜欢你的干劲  但我不能和你...
I like your energy, but I'm not with you.
- 衬衫一湿就不容易撕破  - 听不懂
- When the shirt gets wet, it doesn't break.  - I don't know what that means.
然后...
And then...
好  然后怎么...然后用湿的衬衫  就能...
Okay. And then what...Then with the wet shirt, you...
扭弯栏杆  这很有效
You bend the bars. That's the pay- off.
别让我在那种东西上浪费时间了好吗?
Don't waste my time with stuff like that, okay?
两千年的文明就只是让你能想到这些?
A 2,000- year- old civilization, that's all you can come up with?
你真丢脸  你真丢脸
Shame on you. Shame on you.
拜托  停手吧  很丢人的
Come on. Stop, please. It's embarrassing.
- 看  我说行来着  - 没有  你只说"湿衬衫不容易撕破"
- See? I told you so.  - No, you said, "Wet shirt don't break,"
而不是"尿过的衬衫能扭弯栏杆"
not " Piss shirt bend bar."
- 扭它  - 快帮忙
- Twist it.  - Help.
好  就这样  就是这样
Okay, there. Get it. There you go.
就差一点点  对
Just one more. Yeah.
你真是强壮如牛  来吧  你能做到的
You're as strong as an ox! Go! You can do it!
就是这样  你做到了  成功了
There, you got it! We're gettin' it!
- 帮我顶着  我先穿过去  - 好
- Hold it for me. I'll get through.  - Okay.
不不不  你顶住它  我先穿过去
No, no, no. You hold it and I'll go through.
不要  别用手  住手
No! Not your hand! Stop.
- 帮我顶着  - 再见了  小雏儿
- Hold it.  - Adios, sucker.
- 什么?  - 我只是开个玩笑  快点  过来
- What?  - I'm just kidding. Come on. Go.
我不会留下我老朋友的
I wouldn't leave my old pal there.
过来  真的很挤
Go. Really squeeze.
不不...抓着它  抓着它
No, no, no, no. Grab this, grab that.
在这里继续你的魔术
Work your magic right here.
- 太干了  - 什么?  弄湿它弄湿它  快
- Too dry.  - What? Juice it up. Juice it up. Go.
我做不到  已经没了
I can't! No more!
该死
Ah, damn it.
快出来  小罗伊  施展你的魔法
Come on out, little Roy. Work your magic.
- 快点  - 我正在努力
- Hurry up.  - I'm trying, I'm trying.
- 别看着我  - 放松
- Stop! Don't look at me.  - Relax!
- 放松  会来的  - 谢谢
- Relax. It'll come.  - Thanks.
- 这很有效  不错  很好  - 这就叫放松?
- That helps. Yeah. Good.  - Is that called relax?
警长  感谢上帝你在这儿  拿着那把枪
Sheriff! Oh, thank God you're here. Get the guns!
- 拿着我的书  - 我拿到了
- Get my book!  - I got it!
这位漂亮的小姐是谁?
Whoa, whoa. Wow, who's the pretty lady ?
- 那是我的太太  - 你来这个国家多久了?
- That's my wife.  - How long you been in this country?
- 四天  - 干得漂亮
- Four days.  - Nice work.
你好啊
Hello.
快点  我们走了  搭档
Come on. Let's adios, partner.
你的运气真好
Well, best of luck to you.
估计这是你们民族再见的方式
Guess this is what your people call sayonara.
好像菲度给你添了些麻烦
Looks like Fido's giving you some problems there.
你想要我帮忙吗?
You want me to, uh, give you a hand?
- 不  我自己能做  - 当然  你能
- No, I can do it.  - Sure, you can.
像你这样个没有经验的人怎么到得了卡森市...
How is a greenhorn like you gonna make it to Carson City...
还要救出公主
and rescue this princess?
停下来  停下来...
Stop, stop, stop, stop.
我受不了了  看我怎么做吧
I can't take it any more. Watch me do it.
把它这么弄一下  然后高点的铺上去
Get it like this and you put it up high.
看见没有?  骑的时候它会向后滑
See? It'll drift back when you're riding.
- 好吧  我决定做了  - 做什么?
- All right, I'll do it.  - Do what?
带你去卡森市  帮你救出皮皮公主
Take you to Carson City, help you rescue Princess " Pee Pee."
是佩佩  公主不用你管
Pei Pei. You do not care about the princess.
你不是非常了解我  是吧?
You don't know me very well, do you?
告诉你一件事
Tell you one thing...
我讨厌去想一个无辜的中国贵族在受难
I'd hate to think of an innocent member of Chinese nobility suffering.
我告诉你
Tell you that.
你们那儿的人相信命运是吧?
You people believe in karma over there, right?
我在想我们一再地偶遇一定有个理由
I've been thinking. There must be a reason why we keep running into each other
我以前总是和坏人一起  那种让我无法信任的人
I've ridden with some terrible men...just people I couldn't trust.
但是当我看着你时
But when I look at you,
你有种特别的东西  而且我能看到
there's something different about you, and I can see it.
我能从你的眼中看见
I can see it in your eyes.
就是印第安人所谓的Chippichawa (注: 娼妓)
It's what the Indians call Chippichawa.
- 那是什么?  - Chippichawa是贵族
- What's that?  - Chippichawa is nobility.
而且你绝对有这种气质
And you have it in spades.
你已经给自己找到了个搭档  这与黄金无关  对吧?
You've got yourself a partner. This has nothing to do with gold, okay?
握手吧
Shake on it.
为什么你往手里吐口水?
Why you spitting in your hand?
这是习俗  为了达成交易
Well, it's customary, to seal the deal.
快点  我们出发吧
Come on. Let's go.
这会是一次长途旅程
This is gonna be a long journey.
你们从现在起要当心  听到了吗?  再见
You boys take care now, you hear? Shalom.
再见
Shalom.
出发
Oh. Let's go.
该死
Yee- haw! Goddamn!
看起来你们在这儿也碰到了倒霉事
Looks like y'all had a twister touch down in here.
- 罗伊·奥班诺和他的搭档路过城镇了  - 罗伊·奥班诺?
- Roy O'Bannon and his partner come through town.  - Roy O'Bannon?
罗伊·奥班诺不会再有搭档了  朋友  他已经死了
Roy O'Bannon ain't got no partner, friend. Roy O'Bannon is dead.
他没死  他昨晚和那个上海小子逃狱了
He ain't dead. He busted out of jail last night with the Shanghai Kid.
上海小子?  罗伊有了新同伙?
Shanghai Kid? Roy got a new gang goin'?
那个狗娘养的  两个狗娘养的
That son of a bitch. That two- timin' son of a bitch!
他和那个火车上的中国佬合伙出卖了我们
He double- crossed us with that Chinaman from the damn train!
就是这样  有点倾斜的角度
Just like that. See, at kind of a rakish angle.
- 不错  不错  - 我看起来怎么样?
- Oh, yeah. Oh, yeah.  - How do I look?
我觉得你看上去很棒  我觉得你就像一个真正的牛仔
I think you look great. I think you look like a real cowboy.
非常利落  红色的大手帕
Very dapper, red bandana.
罗伊·奥班诺
Roy O'Bannon.
- 我叫姜文  - 约翰·韦恩?
- My name is Chon Wang.  - John Wayne?
姜文
Chon Wang.
- 真是一个糟糕的牛仔名字  - 为什么?
- That's a terrible cowboy name.  - Why?
不好  拜托  太糟糕了
No, come on, that's not gonna work. That's horrible.
- 太糟了  这条马尾辫子也很糟  - 不要
- That's so bad. And so's the ponytail.  - No!
实际上  它看上去也不是很糟糕
It doesn't look that bad, actually.
永远不要碰我的辫子
Never touch my queue.
那个会杀了我的
That killed! Ow.
- 我们得出发去卡森市了  - 好的
- We have to go to Carson City.  - Okay.
现在  在我们去卡森市之前  我想要教你一些东西  快点
Now, before we go to Carson City, I want to teach you some stuff. Come on.
跟着我做
You just follow me.
- 这是干什么?  - 锻炼敏捷  提高反应力
- What's that?  - Sensitivity. Increased reflexes.
这些是枪  它们可以是你最好的朋友或者最坏的敌人
Now, these are guns. These can be your best friend or worst enemy.
它在我的左手转了一圈  它在我的右手转了一圈
That's a spin in my left hand. That's a spin in my right hand.
这是同时旋转  现在我让你拿着它
That's two spins. Now, here, I'm gonna let you hang onto this.
看见没有?  要小心  时刻准备着
See? Whoa. Be careful. Always be ready. Always be ready.
现在  试着深呼气
Now, try to exhale for long- range shots,
浅吸气
inhale for short- range.
好了  现在捂住你的耳朵  因为声音会很大
All right, now cover up your ears, 'cause this could be loud.
捂住你的耳朵
Cover up your ears.
我像一匹野马  你无法驯服我
I am like a wild horse. You can't tame me.
虽然你把燕麦放在槽中  我每天都会来吃一点
You put the oats in the pen, though, and I'll come in for a nibble every day.
可一旦你关上那道门  我就会跳过栅栏  让你永远看不见我
But if you ever shut that gate, I'll jump the fence. You'll never see me again.
关于你的丈夫...这并不是针对他
Thing about your husband...and this is nothing against him,
因为我真的喜欢他...
because I really like him...
他来自一个非常男权主义的社会
he comes from a very male- dominated society.
我就这么说吧
Let me put it this way...
我的马肯定不是我最好的朋友
my horse is definitely not my best friend.
内华达州  卡森市
现在人们会古怪地看着你
Now, people start looking at you funny,
你只需说  "你好  伙计"
all you gotta say is, " Howdy, partner."
- 你好  伙计?  - 在他们认为你慢脑筋之前说出来
- Howdy, partner?  - Faster than that or people will think you're slow in the head.
- 你好  伙计  - 你好  伙计
- Howdy, partner.  - Howdy, partner.
- 只需跟着我说  你好  伙计  - 你好  伙计
- Just follow my lead. Howdy, partner.  - Howdy, partner.
- 你好  伙计  - 就在那里停放好
- Howdy, partner.  - Just park it right there.
不怎么管用啊
It's not working.
有些人并不像我那么有耐心  所以今天不是很友好
Some people aren't as tolerant as I am. Not very friendly today.
约翰  你要...
John, what are you...
约翰...
John...
好疼
Ow. Hurt.
还要努力学学的
Okay. We gotta work on that.
行了  约翰  直起来走路
Here you go, John. Straighten up here.
- 罗伊  很疼  - 我知道  约翰
- Roy, it hurts so bad.  - I know, John,
如果你像这样走路  我可不和你一起走
but I'm not gonna walk with you if you walk like that.
我试试
I'll be okay.
- 罗伊  是你  - 真见鬼
- Hey, Roy. It's you.  - Holy shit!
我成了通缉犯了  你看看
I'm a wanted man. Look at this!
- 五百美金  可真不少  - 让我看看
- Five hundred bucks! That's a lot of money.  - Let me see.
- 画的很好  - 小心点  小心点
- Nice picture.  - Careful, careful.
你看看  你知道这意味着什么吗?
Wow, look at this. Do you know what this means?
- 这会把少女迷疯的  - 真的吗?
- This will drive the girls crazy.  - Really?
没错  是真的  快  我们把它们都撕下来
Yes, really. Come on, let's get a couple more of these.
- 不坏嘛  - 我也被通缉了
- It's not bad.  - I'm wanted too!
- 什么?  - 这个
- What?  - This.
拜托  不对吧
Oh, come on. That's not right.
我知道  我不是从上海来的
I know. I'm not from Shanghai.
不会吧  一个共犯也要一千美金?
No! $1 ,000 for a sidekick?
- 一定是在开玩笑  - 小心点
- You gotta be kidding me.  - Be careful.
司法体制已经完蛋了
Justice system's all screwed up.
一个连骑马都不会的人竟然还有个很酷的绰号 上海小子
Man can't even ride a horse, and that's a really cool nickname...Shanghai Kid.
这就像是对它的一种...
It's like, got a snap to it that...
麻烦了  约翰  过来  快过来
Uh oh, trouble. John, come here. Get over here.
把他们困在这里  伙计们
Tie 'em up over here, fellas.
- 怎么了?  - 嘘
- What's going on?  - Shh.
你好  伙计
Howdy, partner.
上帝啊  竟然有一队  他们应该不是在找我们的
Oh, my God, it's a posse. They can't be looking for us.
- 一队什么?  - 估计他们只是打这儿路过
- What's " posse"?  - Oh, I think they're passing us by.
他好像是内森·范·克里夫警长  那个有精神病的杀手
It looked like Marshal Nathan Van Cleef, the psychotic killer.
罗伊·奥班诺  我是内森·范·克里夫警长
Roy O'Bannon! This is Marshal Nathan Van Cleef.
- 噢 - 我知道你们藏在里面
- Ohh!  - We know you're hidin 'in there.
上帝啊  真的是他  就是他
Oh, God, it is him. It is him.
你最好扔掉你的左轮手枪  举手出来投降
Why don't you throw down Your six- shooters and come out With your hands up.
还有和你一起的那个人渣
And that goes for the scum you're ridin' with too.
- 他嬴了  - 罗伊  罗伊  没事的
- He won.  - Roy, Roy, it's okay.
不  这怎么会没事  住手  你不了解这个家伙
No, it's not okay! Stop! You don't know this guy!
让我和他们说说  记着  我们要去救公主的
Let me talk to them. Remember, we have to save the princess.
你要干什么?  站...
What are you doin'? St...
- 放轻松  伙计们  - 他们为什么开枪打我?
- Go easy, fellas.  - Why are they shooting at me?
就是"上海小子先生"这怎么了?  我是个通缉犯?
What happened to " Mr. Shanghai Kid"? "Oh, I'm a wanted man"?
- 为什么?  - 因为你是个逃犯
- Why?  - 'Cause you're an outlaw.
- 我不是一个逃犯  - 住口  你这个坏人
- I am not an outlaw!  - Stop! You're a bad guy!
- 看看那张海报吧  上面都写了什么?  - 把少女迷疯
- Look at that poster. What does that say?  - Drives girls crazy.
把少女迷疯?  你是把一队警察迷疯了
Drives girls crazy? Drives the posse crazy.
你让他们想绞死你  吊死你  因为你是个坏人
Makes them want to hang you, string you up, because you're a bad guy.
- 给你们二十秒时间考虑...  - 上帝啊  给我们一分钟吧
- You got 20 seconds...  - Aw, God! Give us a minute!
绕到后面去  先生们
Go around back gentlemen.
别让他耍花招
Make sure he isn't trying to pull the saddle over our eyes
记着  我要活捉那个中国佬
Remember, I want the Chinaman alive.
我不是坏人
I'm not a bad guy.
你是坏人  你和我在一起  你就是一个坏人
You're a bad guy. You're with me, you're a bad guy.
你拉我下水的
Hey, you put me in this situation!
- 我是好人  你是坏人  - 不  我们两个都是坏人
- I'm the good guy, you're the bad guy!  - No! We're both bad guys!
- 不  只有你是坏人  你去告诉他们  - 不
- No, only you're the bad guy! You go out there and tell them!  - No!
- 我不出去  你自己出去吧  - 不  你必须去
- I'm not going out there! You go out there!  - No, you have to go!
- 我干的吗?  - 不错嘛
- Did I just do that?  - Not bad.
我不会空手道  但是我会"抓狂"  而且我也会用的
I don't know karate, but I know " karazy," and I will use it.
里面到底怎么了?
What the hell is going on in there?
你还好吗?
You okay?
你只是把我从窗户扔出来而已
You just threw me through a window.
你拿到了那些黄金?
You got that gold?
什么?  黄金?  什么黄金?
What? Gold? What gold?
答错了
Wrong answer.
等等  我...我没武器  我没带武器的
Wait. I'm...I'm unarmed. I'm unarmed!
我没有枪  等等  我没有枪  我...
No gun. Hold on, no gun. I don't...
我是没带武器  你不能射一个没带枪的人
I'm unarmed! You can't shoot an unarmed man.
- 别担心  我帮你  - 不  约翰  不要  约翰...
- Don't worry. I help you.  - No, John. No, no. John! John...
为荣誉而战  你会赢的
Fight with honor. You will win.
你他妈的有精神病啊?  这就是他们在皇家卫兵学校教你的?
Are you frickin' insane? Is that what they teach you in Imperial Guard School?
- 什么...  - 捡起来
- What...  - Pick 'em up.
这不是上海小子吗?
If it ain't the Shanghai Kid.
我们来跳个儿童舞怎么样?
How about we make the Kid dance?
来吧  你能跳得更好的
Oh, come on! You can do better than that.
你不该抢这趟火车的  孩子
You robbed the wrong train, son.
- 警长  我觉得...  - 闭嘴  把你的枪捡起来
- Look, Marshal, I think that if...  - Just shut up and put on your guns.
这很危险的  你知道吗?
This is serious, you know?
我们不是为这个回来的
We don't come back from this.
真是个平庸的想法
That's the general idea.
你在干什么?
What the hell you doin'?
别拖延时间了  快点  来吧  孩子
Stop procrastinating. Come on. Hurry up, son.
住嘴  我不会让你小瞧的  明白吗?
Stop it! I'm not gonna let you cheapen it. All right?
这是场决斗  很神圣的
This is a duel. It's a sacred thing.
而且很美  我们和动物的区别就在于此
It's beautiful. It's what separates us from the animals.
我不会怨恨你的  准备好了吗?
Whew! I do not envy you. You ready?
为什么不转过来像个男人那样面对我?
Why don't you turn and face me like a man?
为什么不按照各自的做法?  怎么样?
Why don't you do it your way and I'll do it my way? How about that?
来吧  罗伊  你能做到的
Oh, come on, Roy. You can do it.
不行  你做不到  他会杀了你的
Oh, no, you can't. He's gonna kill you.
- 一...  - 他会把你打飞的
- One.  - He's gonna blow you away.
来吧  罗伊  不要那么想
Come on, Roy. Don't think like that.
二...
Two.
没错  要有信心
Oh, yeah. Be positive.
想象自己是子弹  是弹头
Be the bullet. Be the lead bullet.
- 我要死了  - 三...
- I'm about to die.  - Three.
罗伊
Roy!
决斗取消
Duel's off!
罗伊
Roy!
你坏事了  约翰
You blew it, John!
不能妨碍一个正在决斗中的人
Never interrupt a man in the middle of a duel.
我可以搞定他  你差点害死我  我就要搞定他了
I had him. That's what kills me. I had him! I had him!
大家小心啊!
现在你知道给你抬轿的人的感受了吧
Now you know how it feels to haul you around in that sedan chair.
我绝不会向你低头的
I will never bow to you.
好好看看这些脸
Take a good look at these faces.
如果你企图逃跑
If you attempt to escape,
我会每小时杀一个工人...
I will kill one worker every hour...
直到找到你为止
until you are found.
从她开始杀
Starting with this one.
别让他看见你受苦
Do not let him see you suffer.
我知道你是谁
I know who you are.
请别告诉任何人
Please, tell no one.
你称这是个特别的藏身之处?
You call this a special hideout?
是的  它是  约翰
Yes, it is, John.
它还是个收集情报的好地方
It's also a good place to gather intelligence,
因为每个经过卡森市的人都逃不过这些人的耳目
'cause no one passes through Carson City without these people hearing about it.
- 你会向他们询问公主的下落吗?  - 是的  先生  我会的
- Would you ask them about the princess  - Yes, sir, I will.
而且我不管这会有多丢脸
And I don't care how ugly it gets.
不问过每一个人我决不休息  可以了吧?
I'm not gonna rest until I've pumped everybody in there for information, okay?
- 你好  罗伊  - 罗伊  - 你们好啊  女士们
- Hi, Roy.  - Roy.  - Hello, ladies.
给这对亡命之徒让让路吧
Make way for a couple of desperados.
很高兴再次见到你  罗伊先生
Nice to see you again, Mr. O'Bannon.
- 你好  - 罗伊
- Greetings. Hello.  - Roy.
没错  我们在这里会找到些情报的  相信我
Oh, yeah, we're gonna get some information here. Trust me.
这不是个藏身的好地方
This is not a proper hiding place.
拜托  约翰  让我们放松一下
Oh, come on, John. Let's relax for a little bit.
- 来喝一杯  - 不  我要去找公主
- Here, have a drink.  - No. I wanna find the princess.
我也要去  但是我们没法在卡森市挨家挨户的找她
So do I, but we can't exactly go door to door in Carson City looking for her.
- 不要忘了  我们正被通缉呢  - 都是你害的
- Don't forget, we're wanted men.  - Only because of you.
对对对  每件事都是我的错
Yeah, yeah, yeah. Everything's my fault.
公主是个什么样的人?
So, what's the princess like?
约翰  公主长得怎么样?  她很漂亮吗?
John, what's the princess like? Is she pretty?
- 还是非常讨厌?  - 你不能议论她
- Is she a pain in the neck?  - You are not fit to talk about her.
约翰  你最好记得你在哪里
John, you better remember where you are.
这是西方  不是东方
This is the West. It's not the East.
- 记住了吗?  - 但是太阳还是在东方升起...
- Remember?  - And the sun may rise where I come from...
行了行了  你这些废话我知道了
Blah, blah, blah. I know.
很好  你还记得
Good. You remember.
- 她是单身吗?  她还是单身吗?  - 什么?
- Is she single? Is she single?  - What?
她已婚了吗?  我可以娶她吗?
Is she married? Is she available?
只有皇室成员可以
Only to a member of the Imperial family.
你是一位皇室成员吗?  我看不像
Are you a member of the Imperial family? I don't think so.
那是个笑话吗  约翰?  那是个笑话
Was that a joke, John? That was a joke.
约翰  那是你的第一个笑话
John, that was your first joke.
我们来干一杯  为你的第一个笑话
We gotta have a toast. Your first joke.
- 没错  没错  - 不是
- Yes. Yes.  - No.
快点  喝一杯
Come on. Drink.
- 就一杯  - 行
- Just one.  - Okay.
但是不要再议论公主了
But don't talk about the princess any more.
以名誉担保
Word of honor.
行酒令很有意思的
Be fun to play a drinking game.
- 你会中国的酒令吧?  - 不会
- You know any Chinese drinking games?  - No.
每个国家有酒令的  你肯定也知道一个
Every country has a drinking game. You must know one.
就一个?
Just one?
螃蟹一  脚八个  两头儿尖尖这么大的个儿
眼一挤呀, 脖一缩, 爬呀爬呀过沙河
两个好啊该谁喝, 三个三个该谁喝,
五个五个该谁喝, 两个两个该你喝!
- Uno mas  - Uno...什么?
- Uno mas?  - Uno...What?
- 再来  Uno mas  - 好
- One more. Uno mas.  - Okay.
螃蟹一, 脚八个, 两头儿尖尖这么大的个儿
眼一挤呀  脖一缩  爬呀爬呀过沙河...
不  我输了?  再来
No! I lost? One more.
我好迷惘  约翰
I'm so lost, John.
百分之九十的时间我甚至不知道自己在西部这里干什么
Ninety percent of the time, I don't even know what I'm doin' out here in the West.
糟糕的亡命徒
Terrible outlaw.
- 不  你是一个优秀的亡命徒  - 拜托  我总是把事情搞砸了
- No, you're a good outlaw.  - Stop, please. I'm a screw up.
- 不  我才是呢  看看我这些伤疤  - 不对
- No, I am screw up. Look at my scar.  - No.
一个是因为执勤时迟到了
One for arriving late At a guard duty.
还有一个是因为掉了军棍  你算不错了  我看见过你这样
One for dropping fighting stick. You good. I saw you.
我唯一擅长的事就是胡吹神侃
The only thing I'm good at is talking.
- 是真的  - 约翰
- It's true.  - John.
- 啊？ - 拿开你的手  约翰
- Huh?  - Take your hand off me, John.
再来玩会儿?
One more game?
不  不喝了  就这样了
No. No more drinking. That's it.
- Uno mas?  - 不玩了  约翰  不玩了
- Uno mas?  - No mas, John. No mas.
罗伊?
Roy?
- 你能过来吗?  - 菲菲?
- Are you coming?  - Fifi?
你那个看起来很搞笑的朋友是谁?
So, who's your funny- looking friend?
我不知道
I don't know.
他是个我碰到的疯狂的皇家卫兵
He's this crazy Imperial Guard I met.
他...他真的很搞笑
He's- He's really funny.
这家伙歇斯底里的
The guy's hysterical.
我们正在玩游戏  你看见了吗?  我们只是在玩那个酒令
We were just playing...Did you see us? We were just playing that game.
姜文开始...
John's going...
接着我就这样...虽然不明白他说的是什么  但是...
And I was going...You can't really understand what he's saying, but...
罗伊  罗伊  我没想到你和一个中国佬混在一起
Roy? Roy? I never figured you for riding with a Chinaman.
其实我并不是真正地和他一起闯荡  菲菲
Well, I'm not exactly riding with him, Fifi .
他不是我的朋友  你知道的  我是说  他是个中国佬
He's not my friend, you know. I mean, he's a Chinaman.
好的  很好
Well, that's good.
我是说...你们真的...
I mean...And you really...
你们这些人在议论他是什么人?
Were you guys talking about who he was?
我们来谈点别的东西吧
Let's talk about something else.
你看起来很迷人  不是吗?
Don't you look delicious?
- 发生了什么事?  - 很好
- What's going on?  - Well.
- 是你  - 这不是上海小子吗
- You!  - If it isn't the Shanghai Kid.
给你
Here.
谢谢你
Thank you.
谢谢
Ahh. Thank you.
约翰  快点  我们得走了
John, come on. We gotta get going.
- 警长在楼下  - 不对不对  警长在那儿呢
- The marshal's downstairs.  - No, no, Marshal's in there.
约翰  你对他做了什么?
Oh, man, John. What'd you do to him?
- 快点  我们走  - 不
- Come on. Let's get going.  - No!
- 我不和你一起走  - 快点  约翰  该死  你喝醉了
- I don't wanna ride with you.  - Come on, John. Damn, you're a mean drunk.
- 马儿  - 好吧
- Hi, horsey!  - All right. Shh, shh, shh.
- 现在是"呀呼"的时间  - 呀...什么?
- All right, it's time for a "yee- haw".  - Yee- what?
罗伊专用
Shh, shh, shh. Roy O'Bannon special.
我们跳下去  骑在马背面上  大喊"呀呼"
We jump off, land on the back of the horse, yell "yee- haw".
然后就骑马离开  怎么样?
and ride off, all right?
看着我做  然后跟着做  呀呼
Watch me and do exactly as I do it. Yee- haw!
- 马头在哪儿?  - 约翰
- Hyah! Where's the head?  - John!
约翰  起来
John, get up !
抓住他们
Tie 'em up.
我的马怎么了?  它死了吗?
What happened to my horse? Is he dead?
没有  但是我们快死了  约翰
No, but we are, John.
- 马儿  你睡着了吗?  - 起来
- Hi, horsey. You sleeping?  - Get up.
你们的装备让人很吃惊嘛
Mighty impressive hardware you're packin'.
把你的视线从我的东西上挪开  你这婊子养的
Why don't you get your eyes off my package, you twisted son of a bitch.
- 我希望他该走了  - 轮到你了
- I hope that's him leaving.  - Your turn.
谢谢你  范·克里夫先生
Thank you, Mr. Van Cleef.
好了好了  这里都是什么人呢?
Well, well. What have we here?
我猜是奥班诺先生
Mr. O'Bannon, I presume.
我能喝杯水吗?  我口干...
Can I get a drink of water? I got cotton mouth. Aah!
别再提了
Don't mention it.
这肯定是出名的上海小子
And this must be the famous Shanghai Kid.
- 姜文  - 罗方?
- Chon Wang?  - Lo Fong?
你还记得你的老战友呢
You remember your old comrade- in- arms?
- 嗯？ - 我记得一个卖国贼
- Hmm?  - I remember a traitor.
我感到一股仇恨
I'm sensing some bad blood here.
黄金在哪儿?
Where is the gold?
佩佩公主在哪儿?
Where's Princess Pei Pei?
住手  拜托  我们是人  我们不是Pinata
Stop. Come on. We're men. We're not pinatas.
(Pinata: 墨西哥小孩过生日时蒙眼乱打的容器)
好吗?  而且我们在被威胁  我们也不想做硬汉
Okay? And we're really hung over. We 're not trying to be tough guys.
你想谈论黄金  我们就谈论黄金
You wanna talk about the gold, let's talk about the gold.
那么是你拿到了我的黄金?
So, you have my gold?
- 你的黄金?  - 是的  黄金在我们手里
- Your gold?  - Yes, we have the gold.
- 在哪儿?  - 黄金在一个安全的地方
- Then where is it?  - The gold's in a safe place.
他说的是真的吗?
Is he telling the truth?
不是
No.
很好  约翰  干得漂亮  那就用你的脚想个办法
Ow ! Nice, John. Way to go. Way to think on your feet.
他不能撒谎的  他被皇家法律约束着
He cannot lie. He is bound by Imperial decree.
皇家法律
Imperial decree.
为什么你不能多认识一下你现在并不是在中国...
When are you gonna learn you're not in China any more?
他不会"学习"  他只懂服从命令
He will never learn. He can only follow orders.
至少我还有我的尊严
At least I still have my honor.
奴隶是没有尊严的
Slaves have no honor.
- 不  不  - 嘿
- No! No!  - Hey!
现在你永远都回不了中国了
Now you can never go back to China.
你搞砸了  你搞砸了  伙计
You blew it. Whoo! You blew it, man.
相信我  你不该剪掉他的头发的
You do not want to cut his hair off, trust me.
不要怪我  孩子
Nothing personal, boys.
永远对皇帝效忠
My loyalty is to the emperor.
没错  约翰  我听到的都是关于皇帝的
Yeah, John, I heard all about the emperor.
肯定是个不怎么样的人
Must be a hell of a man.
他只有十二岁
He's only 12.
你在玩我吗?  你站在这儿让绳子套住你的脖子等死
Are you kidding me? You're sitting here with a noose around your neck...
就是为了一个蛋蛋还没长出来的人效命?
ready to die for someone whose balls haven't even dropped?
根据内华达州的法律赋予我的权利
By virtue of the authority vested in me through the territory of Nevada,
我宣布对这两个人实行绞刑
I do hereby order these men to hang by their necks...
直到他们停止挣扎
until their feet quit kicking.
你们马上就要下地狱了  孩子们
You're goin' to hell, boys,
你们的马会带你们去
and your horses are taking you there.
勒死他们
Tighten 'em up.
吊死他们  吊死他们
Hang 'em! Hang 'em!
小心点  你这小混蛋
Hey! Watch it, you little punk.
吊死他们  吊死他们
Hang 'em! Hang 'em! Hang 'em! Hang 'em!
约翰  你在干什么?
John, what are you doing?
发生了什么事?  停住那些马
What the hell is goin' on here? Stop those horses!
停住它们
Stop them!
快拉  快拉
Pull it! Pull it!
救命
Help me
别只是站在那儿  去追他们
Well, don't just stand there! Go after them!
听到小溪的水流声了吗  约翰?
Will you listen to this creek, John?
我从没发现这个声音这么美
I've never noticed what a beautiful melody a creek makes.
从来没有
I've never taken the damn time.
看着这些山和这些树
Look at these mountains and these trees.
见鬼  看看这些绿树  过来  我甚至不知道名字...
Hell, look at these green trees. Come here. I don't even know the names...
我们要了解下这些绿树的名字  过来
We're gonna learn the names of these green trees. Come here.
我想要你看看
I want you to look at these.
我们就不能...约翰  你在做什么?
Can we not...John, what are you doing?
你还在心疼你的头发?
Are you still worried about your hair?
约翰  听我说  你太爱虚荣了
John, listen to me. You're very vain.
等你七十岁的时候  你的马尾辫...
By the time you're 70, your queue, your ponytail...
会焕然一新
will be as good as new.
- 你在干什么?  - 我要离开
- What are you doing?  - I'm leaving.
我们就不能休息几秒钟  约翰?  我们刚刚幸免一死
Can we not take two seconds, John? We just cheated death.
快点  花点时间看看这些山
Come on. Let's look at these mountains for a second.
- 好吧  我去拿东西  天哪  你真让人难以置信  - 我自己走
- Okay, let me get my stuff. God, you're unbelievable.  - I'm going alone.
你要怎...约翰  你说什么?
What are you...John, what are you talking about?
- 我听到了  - 你听到什么了?
- I heard you.  - You heard me. Okay.
在金发女郎的房间
At Goldie's.
你说我不是你的朋友
You said I wasn't your friend.
约翰...
John...
等一下  约翰  我当时是和一个女人说的
Hold on a second, John. I was talking to a girl.
- 那是...你没听到来龙去脉...  - 罗伊
- It was...That's taken out of context. That's not...  - Roy.
你是对的  我怎么可能是你的朋友
You were right. How could I ever be your friend?
我只是个中国佬
I'm just a Chinaman.
等等  约翰  对不起  我不是那个意思...
Hold on, John. I'm sorry. I didn't mean it to...
再见  罗伊
Sayonara, Roy.
大家小心啊
在这里等一下
Wait here.
请进
Please.
你走了段很长的路
You have come a long way.
我希望你寻找的公主值得你这么奉献
I hope the princess you seek is worthy of such devotion.
把她带回去是我的职责
It is my duty to bring her home.
我甚至带了她的最喜欢的书
I even brought her favorite book.
你真是太好了
That's very kind of you.
但是如果你发现公主不愿意回紫禁城
But what if you found the princess and she did not wish to go back
那怎么办?
to the Forbidden City?
她为什么想要留在这里?
Why would she want to stay here?
也许她在这里比她回到中国...
Maybe she can do more for the people here...
能为她的人民做更多的事
than she could back in China.
佩佩公主
Princess Pei Pei.
请不要引起注意
Please, don't draw attention.
请站起来
Please. Stand up!
公主  你必须跟我走
Princess, you have to come with me.
不行  不能让罗方发现我走了
I cannot. Fong cannot find me missing.
公主  我不能把你留在这里
Princess, I cannot leave you here.
请站起来
Please, standup!
不要下跪  起来
Don't bow! Get up!
起来
Get up!
你必须走了
You must go.
如果我走了  罗方会乱杀无辜的
If I leave, Fong will begin to kill the others.
把你带回去是我的职责
It is my duty to bring you home.
我命令你快走
I command you to go.
走
Go!
举起手来  秃驴
Reach for the sky, baldy!
没错  罗伊来了
That's right. It's Roy.
我打扰你们了吗?
Am I interrupting?
我一直跟着你  怎么了?
I followed you. So what?
你想让我怎么样  让你漂泊?  你是一个生手啊
What am I supposed to do, let you wander off? You're a greenhorn.
你会死在这里的
You'll get killed out here.
快点  我们必须离开这里  搭档  快点
Come on! We gotta adios out of here, partner! Come on!
你终于跟我走了
Hyah! You gotta stick with me.
别忘了  我们还要去解救公主
Don't forget, we got a princess to save.
公主!
把刀放下
把金子拿过来
公主
代我向皇帝问好  公主
Give my regards to the emperor, Princess.
- 姜文?  - 姜文?  - 姜文?
- Chon Wang?  - Chon Wang?  - Chon Wang?
没错  约翰·韦恩在这儿
That's right, Johnny Wayne is here.
是我
Hey, it's me.
你为什么剪了他的头发?
Why did you cut his hair?
我警告过你  但是你不听
I tried to warn you, But you wouldn't listen.
快  放下枪
Go on, drop the gun.
现在  踢给我
Now, slide it over.
是她吗?
Is that her?
她很漂亮
She's pretty.
把握住喽
Grab her.
快点  我们离开这里  伙计们
Come on. We'll take it from here, guys.
我不会让你把公主带回去的
你以为你是谁啊
你忘了你的任务了?
而且公主也不愿意回去
圣旨下, 姜文接旨
约翰  干什么...约翰  起来
John, what...John, get up.
你在干什么...我想我们可以省略这些了吧
What are you...I thought we were past this.
快点  约翰
Come on, John.
奉天承运...
皇帝诏曰  特派三位最勇敢的...
看见没有?  他永远都是个奴隶
Do you see? He will always be a slave.
...皇家卫兵  陪同皇家翻译  一同前往...
...亚美利加国保卫佩佩...
这是西方
This is the West,
不是东方
not the East.
而且太阳也许是从我们那里升起
And the sun may rise where we come from
但是它在这里落下
but here is where it sets.
你用我翻译吗?  公主留下来了
You want me to translate? The princess stays.
公主留下来了
The princess stays.
我要黄金了  你就和公主结婚吧
I grab the gold, You marry the princess.
我们俩搞定罗方  打完收工  任务就完成了
We both hang Fong and call it a day. Mission accomplished.
好了好了
Well, well.
很高兴发现大家都是经常做礼拜的人
Nice to see we're all churchgoers.
婊子养的  他拿着我的枪
Son of a bitch! With my own guns!
很亲切  对吧?
Sweet, ain't it?
怎么样  这个僵局?
How about that? It's a Mexican standoff.
只有我们不会
Only we ain't got no Mexicans.
公主!
不
No!
公主  小心
Princess Pei Pei!
- 保护公主  - 好
快走啊!
- 公主, 快走啊!  - 不走!
- 我打到你了吗?  - 没有
- I hit you?  - No.
但是你真的只差一点点
But you're gettin' really close.
你差点杀了我  差不多已经有十七次了
You've almost killed me, like, 17 times already.
十八  十九  二十
Eighteen, nineteen, twenty!
你今天火气真大
You're on fire today!
公主  你快去救公主
姜文  接着
你怎么逃出这里呢?
How do you survive out here?
什么意思?  这些不是我的...这些枪真的很难用
What's that supposed to mean? These aren't my...These guns are really weird.
不要啊
Oh, man.
上来
快点走
Stay low!
公主  过来
抓住  公主
也许过去的事就该让它过去吧  你射的几枪都很准
Maybe we should let bygones be bygones. You got off some good shots.
我也有几枪射的不错  我们打了个平手
I got off some good ones. Let's call it a tie.
怎么了  奥班诺?  没子弹了?
What's the matter, O'Bannon? Out of bullets?
不是  还有一发
No, I got one left.
告诉你我接下来要怎么做吧
Tell you what I'll do.
我取出所有的子弹  只留一发
I'll take out all my bullets but one.
这样我们就平等了  怎么样?
And that way, we'll be even. How's that?
好  听起来很公平
Okay. That sounds fair.
你肯为我那么做吗?
You'd do that for me?
会啊
Oh, yeah.
当然会了
You bet I would.
我们数三下后出来
We come out on three.
我知道  但是...得让我来数
I know, but- but let me count.
为荣誉而战  很好
Fight with honor. Okay.
为荣誉而战...好了  一...
Fight with...Okay. One!
二  二点五...
Two! Two and a half!
二点七八...
Two and seven- eights!
三
Three!
怎么可能会这样?
How the hell did that happen?
真是个奇迹
It's a miracle.
我是无敌的
I am invincible.
罗伊
Roy!
无敌的
Invincible!
- 现在你的死期到了  - 再见  搭档
- Now it's time for you to die.  - Adios, partner.
- 他没事吧?  - 没事
罗伊
Roy!
他拿走了黄金
He took the gold.
你关心的只有黄金吗?
Is that all you care about is the gold?
你真丢脸
Shame on you.
人生里有很多东西比钱更重要  我希望有一天你能了解
There's more to life than money. I hope you learn that one day.
发生了什么事?
What happened?
什么?  没什么没什么  我只是杀了他而已  你怎么样?
What? Nothing, nothing. I just killed him. How'd you do?
怎么做到的?
How?
你什么意思  怎么做到的?  我是用自己的枪打死他的
What do you mean, how? I shot him with my gun.
拜托  告诉我真相
Come on. Tell me the truth.
让人难以置信  你错过了一个奇迹  我当时只剩下一发子弹
It was unbelievable. You missed a miracle. I had one bullet left.
他却有无数发  他骗我说他也只有一发了
He had, like, a million left. He lied to me and told me that he only had one too.
但是...但是这时...但是当他...
But-But when...But when he...
将在外, 军令有所不受
- 她留下来了?  - 是的
- She's staying?  - Yes.
- 我能站起来吗?  - 可以
- Can I stand?  - Yes.
举手投降吧  奥班诺
Reach for the sky, O'Bannon!
那是我的台词  他偷了我的团伙  他还要偷我的台词
That's my line. He stole my gang, he's stealing my lines.
- 真是难以置信  - 罗伊  罗伊
- That's unbelievable.  - Roy! Roy!
回来
Get back!
住手  住手  是华莱士
Stop, stop. It's Wallace.
罗伊
Hey, Roy
我们知道你和火车上的那个黄种人一起暗算我们
we know you been moonlightin' on us with that old yellow fella from the train!
你们留在这里  这不是你们的战斗
You guys, you stay here. This isn't your battle.
不  我们一起去  我们是搭档
No, we stick together. We are partners.
太好了
That's beautiful.
你从后门出去
You go out the back door.
- 不  - 不要担心  公主
- No.  - Don't worry, Princess.
我答应你  我们会再见的
I promise you, I will see you again.
你一旦答应...
That which you have promised...
就必须要做到
you must perform.
小心保护公主
姜文
- 让开  - 为什么?
- Get out of the way!  - Why?
- 快点!  - 为什么?  你要干什...
- Come on!  - Why? What are you...
- 你在干什么?  你疯了吗?  - 不  约翰  住手  住手
- What are you doing? Are you crazy?  - No, John, stop, stop.
他们打不到我的  冥冥中会发生一些事  是奇迹
They can't touch me. Something happened back there. It was a miracle.
- 不会...  - 笨驴  听到了没?
- There's no way...  - Hey, smart-ass! Do you hear me?
时间到了  奥班诺  台词彩排结束了
Time's up, O'Bannon! It's the end of the line!
我们能搞定这些家伙的  是的  我们能搞定的
We can take these guys. Yep, we can take them.
你出不出来?
Are you comin' out or ain't you?
枪
Gun.
你真是"上海小子"啊
You really are the Shanghai Kid.
很高兴与你合作  搭档
Nice riding with you, partner.
我们数三下就出去  我来数
We go out on three. I count.
不  我来数
No, I count.
我们两个一起数
We'll both count.
一  二  三
One, two, three!
- 印第安人  小心  - 不  我的家人  我的家人
- Indians! Look out!  - No! My family! My family!
- 朋友们  兄弟们  - 罗伊
- Friends. Brothers!  - Roy!
我告诉你  我们一直当你是笨蛋  但是...
I gotta tell ya, we always figured you for a dumb shit, but, uh,
我们想也许你想回来重新入伙
we was thinkin' maybe you wanna come back and rejoin the gang.
- 所以  你会回来吗?  - 是的  你会回来吗?
- So, uh, what do you  say?  - Yeah, what do you say?
我想我只会参加"即兴表演"
I think I'm just gonna wing it.
好吧
All right.
- 而你们要进监狱  - 那也行
- And you are goin ' to jail.  - That works too.
好  爬虫
How, kimosabe!
站在你旁边真是太好了
Oh, it's nice to be standing here next to you.
我还以为我没有机会谢谢你...
I don't think I've ever gotten a chance to Thank you for...
多次搭救我们
for saving us so many times.
我希望你能了解...我感觉好像我们之间有些隔阂
I wish you could understand what...I feel like there's this gap between us.
比如  我是一个牛仔  你却是一个印第安人
It's like, I'm a cowboy, you're an Indian.
你说"贝壳串珠"  我说"钱" (印第安人用作货币或饰品)
You say "wampum," I say " money."
在某些方面  我只是想...
At a certain point, I just think...
闭嘴  罗伊  你废话太多了
Shut up, Roy. You talk too much.
她...她...她刚才...
Did...Did...She just...
她就在那儿  很准时  带着很大的账本
There she is, right on time, carrying a big, fat payroll.
我不知道我是不是会习惯这个
I don't know if I'll ever get used to this one.
不要担心  你会习惯它的
Don't worry. You'll get used to it.
我向你保证  我们不会让超过一半的女人成为执法人士的
I can guarantee you, we won't get half as many girls being lawmen.
我知道人们都想要什么  但是...
I know we're spoken for, but...
你永远不会知道在某种关系中会发生什么
You never know what's gonna happen in a relationship.
我要去掉我那个亡命徒的名字  我不会再用它了
I gotta get rid of my outlaw name. That's not gonna work any more.
真的?  你会叫自己什么?
Really? What would you call yourself?
我不知道  我想我真正名字是怀亚特·厄普  但是...
I don't know. I mean, my real name's Wyatt Earp, but...
厄普?  真是一个糟糕的牛仔名字
Earp? That's a terrible name for a cowboy.
- 为什么?  - 烂
- Why?  - Bad.
- 真的吗?  - 烂
- Really?  - Bad!
- 那约翰·韦恩是个伟大的牛仔名字?  - 罗伊  看
- And John Wayne's a great cowboy name?  - Roy, look.
他们在那里
There they are.
是的  看看那些业余选手  那是我的
Yep. Look at those amateurs. That's my move!
快点  罗伊  我们去说"你好"
Come on, Roy. Let's go say " howdy."